L compared with T D and N. When you learn to pronounce the L correctly, you'll feel
its similarity with T D and N. Actually, the tongue is positioned in the same place
in the mouth for all four sounds, behind the teeth. The difference is in how and
where the air comes out. T and D. The sound of both T and D is produced by
allowing a puff of air to come out over the tip of the tongue. N. The sound of N
is nasal. The tongue completely all air from leaving through the mouth, allowing
it to come out only through the nose. You should be able to feel the edges of your
tongue touching your teeth as you say N, L. With the L, the tip of the tongue is
securely touching the roof of the mouth behind the teeth, but the sides of the
tongue are dropped down and tensed. This is where L is different from N. With N,
the tongue is relaxed and covers the entire area around the back of the teeth
so that no air can come out. With L, the tongue is very tense and the air comes out
around its sides. At the beginning, it's helpful to exaggerate the position of the
tongue. Look at yourself in the mirror as you stick out the tip of your tongue
between your front teeth. With your tongue in this position, say L several times.
Then try saying it with your tongue behind your teeth, L. This sounds complicated,
but it's easier to do than to describe. Our first exercise, however, must focus on
differentiating the sounds.